{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Mary Birdsall bought a publication from this woman titled The Lily in which she once wrote “Intemperance is the great foe to [women’s] peace and happiness.” This woman inspired Mary Gove Nichols to draft a document against Parisian styles. This woman promoted the “health, comfort, and usefulness” of Libby Miller’s design, which was displayed at the Seneca Falls Convention and took the form of a “Turkish Dress.” An 1851 “craze” was sparked by, for ten points, what suffragette whose name was quickly attached to a style of divided, pant-like dress?",
      "answer": "Amelia Bloomer"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the 1970’s, a Chinese scientist introduced a new recommended treatment for this disease after reading a traditional Chinese medicine source written in 340 AD. Tu Youyou was awarded the 2015 Nobel Prize in medicine for her discovery of a medication used to treat this disease named artemisinin. Individuals with the sickle-cell anemia gene are resistant to, for ten points, what infectious disease that can be avoided by using simple bed nets, thus keeping away Anopheles mosquitoes?",
      "answer": "malaria"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1955, this man accused the US of being a threat to world peace in a speech that promised to “never forget that the first atom bomb was exploded on Asian soil.” In Geneva in 1954, John Foster Dulles snubbed this man’s handshake. This man’s 1976 death triggered the Tiananmen Incident when the Gang of Four removed mourning protestors from the square. The meeting between Mao Zedong and Richard Nixon was arranged by, for ten points, what first Premier of the People’s Republic of China?",
      "answer": "Zhou Enlai"
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer changed his surname so that he could serve with the YMCA during World War I. He reused the finale of his Second Suite for Military Band, “Fantasia on the Dargason,” in his St. Paul’s Suite. A patriotic hymn by Cecil Spring Rice named “I Vow To Thee, My Country” was set to Thaxted, which was taken from a suite by this man with movements subtitled “The Bringer of War” and “The Bringer of Jollity.” For ten points, name this English composer who depicted Mars and Jupiter in The Planets.",
      "answer": "Gustav von Holst"
    },
    {
      "question": "A subset of this system co-named for Gardner and Salinas allows it to incorporate scientific notation, and the Antoine notation is used to represent numbers in this system. This system was an improvement upon one developed for Napoleon’s army by Charles Barbier; that system was night writing. The Grade 2 variety is the most commonly used English type of this system, which was developed by a man who suffered an accident with an awl as a child. For ten points, name this writing system of raised dots used by the blind.",
      "answer": "braille writing"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man discussed the two halves of Barack Obama’s private and public goals in his book Obama and The Empire. This leader published the newspaper The Accuser while leading a group simply called The Movement, after which he planned an attack on the Moncada Barracks. This leader deposed Fulgencio Batista in a revolution, during which he worked alongside his brother Raul. For ten points, name this longtime leader of communist Cuba who passed away in 2016.",
      "answer": "Fidel Castro"
    },
    {
      "question": "The planners of this event were influenced by an incendiary letter from the doctor Cornelius Rhoads and wished to avenge Pedro Campos’ failed revolution of October 30. Donald Birdzell was struck in the knee during this event, while Leslie Coffelt was mortally wounded. The target of this event had been temporarily moved to the Blair House thanks to ongoing renovations at the White House. Oscar Collazo and Griselio Torresola carried out, for ten points, what 1950 event in which Puerto Rican nationalists targeted the sitting president?",
      "answer": [
        "attempted assassination of Harry Truman",
        "attack on Truman",
        "similar phrasings that don’t imply Truman died"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The inventor of this weapon earlier designed the first double action hemp break. John Henry Parker got a nickname inspired by these weapons, which he used to defend San Juan Hill during the Spanish-American War. Twelve of these weapons were deployed at the Siege of Petersburg. The ten caliber type of this hand-cranked weapon can fire up to 400 rounds a minute. For ten points, name these rapidly firing proto-machine guns that were prominently used in the Civil War and named for their American inventor.",
      "answer": "Gatling guns"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man gave his sister Anna in marriage to Vladimir I in exchange for the Chersonesos military base in the Crimea. This man was ambushed at the Gates of Trajan after successfully relieving Sofia from siege. After his greatest success, this man allegedly blinded 99 out of every 100 prisoners he took, a sight that made rival king Samuel die of shock. For ten points, name this winner of the Battle of Kleidion, a Byzantine emperor known as the “Bulgar-slayer.”",
      "answer": [
        "Basil II or Basil the Bulgar Slayer before mentioned",
        "Basileios II, Basil the Porphyrogenitus,",
        "Basil the Young"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Nearly 1,500 of these objects are held at a museum in Marikina. After a 1992 political upheaval, hundreds of these objects were moved out of the basement of the Malacanang Palace. Upon the opening of a museum for these objects, their original owner remarked “they went into my closets looking for skeletons, but thank God, all they found were” these objects. For ten points, name this collection of luxury fashion items amassed by the “Iron Butterfly” of the Philippines, who wore most of the hundreds of pairs of them.",
      "answer": "Imelda Marcos’ shoes"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At this battle, the winning side assembled a line of 50 artillery pieces between Dill and Tilghman branches. In this battle, a march toward River Road was conducted by Lew Wallace to avoid facing the enemy from the rear. After facing heavy casualties on one day during this battle, the Union commander said “Lick em’ tomorrow, though.” Albert Sidney Johnston was killed during this battle, in which Union forces defended an encampment called Pittsburg Landing. For ten points, name this 1862 Civil War victory for Grant in Tennessee.",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of Shiloh",
          "Battle of Pittsburg Landing before mentioned BONUS:HeavyfightingduringtheBattleofShilohtookplaceatthispositionnearasunkenroad.Possibly a dozen Confederate charges on this position over seven hours eventually forced Benjamin Prentiss to surrender, but it allowed Grant crucial time to set up his defenses. ANSWER: Hornet’s Nest"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Potsdam Conference established this line, which mostly follows a pair of namesake rivers, as Poland’s western border with Germany following World War II.",
        "answer": "Oder-Neisse Line"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A Japanese version of this institution called the Ooku was created by Tokugawa Hidetada. Leaders of another of these institutions held either the title of Haseki or Valide. According to a probably fabricated legend, the Yongle Emperor killed 2800 members of one of these institutions to suppress a scandal. This term generally refers to a reserved domestic space, but has taken on the connotation of a brothel. For ten points, give this term for the quarters of the wives and concubines of imperial Ottoman rulers.",
        "answer": [
          "harem",
          "seraglio",
          "zenanna"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Ottoman harem was located in this palace, the main residence of the Ottoman sultans until the 17th century. It was built by Mehmed II.",
        "answer": "Topkapi Palace"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city was the site of a brief coup known as the Speckputsch. This city’s Margravial Opera House wasbuiltforMargraveFrederick,whoruledaprincipalitynamedforBrandenburgandthiscity.Originally, performances of Parsifal were only allowed within this city’s Festival Hall; that hall, sponsored by Mad King Ludwig, was the site of the premiere of Der Ring des Nibelungen. For ten points, name this Bavarian town which hosts a festival each year devoted to performing the works of Richard Wagner.",
        "answer": "Bayreuth"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mad King Ludwig also sponsored the construction of this castle high in the Bavarian Alps. It inspired Disneyland’s Sleeping Beauty Castle.",
        "answer": "Neuschwanstein Castle"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "While working under this man, William Joseph Hammer discovered what he called a “Phantom Shadow.” An animal that had killed Jesse Blount was used in a famous demonstration filmed by this man’s employees; that animal, named Topsy, was an elephant whose death was used by this man to show the dangers of a technology advocated by George Westinghouse. For ten points, name this opponent of alternating current, an American inventor sometimes known as “The Wizard of Menlo Park.”",
        "answer": "Thomas Alva Edison"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The aforementioned “Edison Effect” is thermionic emission within one of these evacuated containers. Diodes are simple examples of these devices, which were quickly replaced by semiconductor- based transistors in early electronic computers.",
        "answer": "vacuum tubes or electron tube"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At the end of this novel, the protagonist feels “integrated” after his horse tramples his leg. An operation to blow up a bridge in this novel is nearly ruined when the detonators are stolen. The execution of fascist sympathizers in Pilar’s village in this novel parallels a real life massacre in the city of Ronda. The protagonist of this novel is a member of the International Brigades and works for a Republican guerrilla unit under the leadership of Pablo. For ten points, name this novel about Robert Jordan’s service during the Spanish Civil War, a work by Ernest Hemingway.",
        "answer": "For Whom the Bell Tolls"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ernest Hemingway’s only play is titled after this concept, a term coined during the Spanish Civil War by Nationalist general Emilio Mola. This term refers to Mola’s supporters within the city of Madrid who would emerge as his troops approached.",
        "answer": [
          "The Fifth Column",
          "quinta columna"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A siege of this state’s capital was carried out by the Pechenegs during their westward migration. The state’s collapse led to the rise of Galicia-Volhynia and Vladimir-Suzdal and began after the Battle of the Kalka River, which it lost to the Mongols. Yaroslav the Wise led this state in the 11th century, and it was founded by Oleg the Seer, who moved its capital from Novgorod. The Rurikid dynasty led, for ten points, what precursor state to modern Russia?",
        "answer": "Kievan Rus"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Rus was founded by a member of this group, essentially the Greek name for Vikings. Members of this group were employed by the Byzantine Emperor as a personal guard.",
        "answer": [
          "Varangians",
          "the Varangian Guard"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A 1999 song is named from a town in this country, “Bobcaygeon,” [bob-cay-jun] just because the name rhymed with “constellation.” “My Music at Work” and “Locked in the Trunk of a Car” were also released by a Gord Downie-fronted band from this country, The Tragically Hip; the Hip gave their final tour in 2016, ending with a concert watched by 11 million people on the CBC. For ten points, name this country, also home to Arcade Fire, Rush, and Nickelback.",
        "answer": "Canada"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Tragically Hip’s song “Locked in the Trunk of a Car” references this 1970 crisis in which members of the FLQ kidnapped cabinet minister Pierre Laporte, killed him, and left his body in the trunk of a car.",
        "answer": "October Crisis"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Commerce Clause",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Constitutional article in which it appears, granting Congress the power to “regulate Commerce.”",
          "answer": "Article 1 or First Article, etc."
        },
        {
          "question": "Set of anti-Great Depression programs that the Supreme Court commonly attacked with the Commerce Clause.",
          "answer": "New Deal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Substance whose growth for medicinal use was ruled by Gonzales v. Raich to be part of the aggregate economy.",
          "answer": [
            "medical marijuana",
            "equivalents, like weed",
            "pot"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "System of gambling that Champion v. Ames held was interstate commerce, well before Powerball existed.",
          "answer": [
            "lottery",
            "additional information that uses the word lottery"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "2010 act whose individual mandate penalty was ruled permissible as a tax but not a valid use of the Commerce Clause.",
          "answer": [
            "Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act",
            "Obamacare",
            "PPACA"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1824 case that ruled that New York could not regulate steamboat navigation on its waters because it was interstate commerce.",
          "answer": [
            "Gibbons v. Ogden",
            "either",
            "both"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1916 act, struck down by Hammer v. Dagenhart, that banned interstate shipping of goods produced by child labor.",
          "answer": [
            "Keating-Owen Child Labor Act or Bill",
            "Law",
            "Wick’s Act, Bill,"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1995 case that ruled that the Gun Free School Zones Act was unconstitutional because possession of a gun was not part of the aggregate economy.",
          "answer": "US v. Lopez"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Year of the Four Emperors",
      "prompt": "In the year 69 AD...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Roman forces put down a Jewish revolt when they destroyed the Temple in what city?",
          "answer": "Jerusalem"
        },
        {
          "question": "What crazy Roman emperor, who legendarily fiddled as Rome burned, committed suicide?",
          "answer": "Nero Claudius Caesar Augustus Germanicus"
        },
        {
          "question": "What elite bodyguards sold the title of Emperor to several competing men?",
          "answer": "Praetorian Guard"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who became the last of the Four Emperors, putting the Flavian dynasty in control?",
          "answer": "Vespasian"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Batavians invaded Rome by crossing what border river, home to legions loyal to the third of the four emperors?",
          "answer": "Rhine River"
        },
        {
          "question": "What former governor of Hispania was the first emperor to reign that year? He was replaced by Otho.",
          "answer": "Galba"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who was the third emperor, after Otho?",
          "answer": "Vitellius"
        },
        {
          "question": "What ancient village near modern Cremona was the site of two power-shifting battles in AD 69, one of which caused Otho’s suicide?",
          "answer": "First and/or Second Battles of Bedriacum"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Portugal in Asia",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Ocean that Vasco da Gama reached in 1498, the first European to do so by sea.",
          "answer": "Indian Ocean"
        },
        {
          "question": "Trading post near Hong Kong that was transferred to China in 1999.",
          "answer": "Macau"
        },
        {
          "question": "15th century prince who sponsored voyages that reached Cape Verde and the Azores, but not quite Asia.",
          "answer": "Henry the Navigator"
        },
        {
          "question": "Colony in India that served as the headquarters of Portugal’s rule in the Indian Ocean.",
          "answer": "Goa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Colony on the Malay peninsula that attempted to control trade through a namesake strait.",
          "answer": [
            "Portuguese Malacca",
            "Strait of Malacca",
            "additional generic information, like Malacca colony"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Island where Portugal fought the Kingdom of Kandy.",
          "answer": "Sri Lanka or Ceylon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Colony that dominated trade through the Straits of Hormuz. Piri Reis led a 1552 Ottoman expedition to capture this city.",
          "answer": "Muscat"
        },
        {
          "question": "Trading posts established by Portugal throughout Asia. The first was built by near Arguin.",
          "answer": "factory or feitoria"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One side in this war was forced to abandon aiding a Jacobite uprising after a storm off the Galician coast turned its fleet back. During this war, General Villasur was defeated by the Pawnee while attempting to curb French settlement in Nebraska. This war began after Philip V violated the Treaty of (20 pts)",
        "Utrecht by claiming the French throne after Louis XIV’s death. Sardinia was transferred to Savoy as part of the 1720 Treaty of (10 pts)",
        "The Hague, ending this war. For ten points, name this war in which Spain unsuccessfully fought a namesake alliance of Great Britain, France, the Holy Roman Empire, and the Dutch Republic."
      ],
      "answer": "War of the Quadruple Alliance"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This word titles a 1938 film by Leni Riefenstahl that features footage of the first torch relay. A “Modern” work of this title features a man in a brown coat on the right leaning on a purple slope and looking away from the viewer at the title figure; that work is by (20 pts)",
        "Paul Cezanne. Another artwork of this name appears to feature a demi-mondaine, based on her pearl earrings, the Oriental shawl she lies on, and the orchid in her hair; that apparent prostitute lies on a bed, looks at the viewer, and is attended by a (10 pts)",
        "black servant. For ten points, give this common name shared by a masterpiece of E´douard Manet [man-ay]."
      ],
      "answer": "Olympia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A siege in this conflict included the death of a man immortalized in John Greenleaf Whittier’s poem “Burial of Barber.” Franklin Coleman’s killing of Charles Dow sparked this conflict’s (20 pts)",
        "Wakarusa War. A prominent group in this conflict was inspired by David Rice Atchison’s rhetoric to cast ballots in a certain state. The (10 pts)",
        "“Border Ruffians” were one faction of this conflict, which was inflamed by the proposal of the Lecompton Constitution. The sack of Lawrence occurred during, for ten points, what pre-Civil War conflict between pro-slavery and anti-slavery factions in a Midwestern state?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Bleeding Kansas",
        "Bloody Kansas",
        "the Border War",
        "Wakarusa War before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this country, Jacobina Mentz Maurer ordered the killing of enemy families in the Revolt of the Muckers. A rebel government in this country was established in Belem in the State of Grao-Para. Muslims in this South American country wore necklaces with images of Jean-Jacques Dessalines during a revolt in (20 pts)",
        "Bahia. High taxes on charque sparked a rebellion in Rio Grande do Sul in this country, whose rebels were supported by Giuseppe Garibaldi in the Ragamuffin War. This country’s independence was (10 pts)",
        "announced at the Cry of Ipiranga by its first emperor, Pedro I. For ten points, name this South American country once led from Rio de Janeiro."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Federative Republic of Brazil",
        "Empire of Brazil"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A man from one city of this name promises to pay back fourfold for anything he had defrauded. That man, Zacchaeus, was the chief tax collector of that city, which is also the destination of the man who is helped by the (20 pts)",
        "Good Samaritan. A curse killed the first two sons of anyone who tried to rebuild another city of this name. The prostitute Rahab was spared from the destruction of this city by (10 pts)",
        "hiding two spies under bundles of flax on her roof. For ten points, give the common name of two Biblical cities, the first of which was destroyed by Israelites circling its walls for seven days."
      ],
      "answer": "Jericho"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a 1968 phone call, this man asked for “any other way to monkey wrench it,” as recorded in notes discovered by Jack Farrell in 2016. Those notes, which include a point to “keep Anna Chennault working on SVN,” were taken by this man’s future Chief of Staff, (20 pts)",
        "H.R. Haldeman, and prove that this man tried to hurt Hubert Humphrey’s presidential campaign by sabotaging peace negotiations in (10 pts)",
        "Vietnam. For ten points, name this man who, shortly after, won the 1968 election and expanded the Vietnam War as the successor to Lyndon Johnson."
      ],
      "answer": "Richard Nixon"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Displays at this event included a barometer that based observations on the movement of leeches and Frederick Bakewell’s early version of a fax machine. An object known as the “Mountain of Light” that had once been owned by (20 pts)",
        "Nader Shah was displayed during this event. The man who devised the first Christmas card, Henry Cole, helped organize this event. The Koh-i-Noor Diamond was on display during this event, which was attended by writers like George (10 pts)",
        "Eliot and Charles Dickens. Prince Albert helped plan, for ten points, what 1851 exhibition in London, held in a magnificent plate glass building?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Crystal Palace Exhibition",
        "The Great Exhibition of the Works of Industry of All Nations"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s presence on the first board of trustees at Jane Addams’ Hull House reflected his interest in the formation of a democratic community. This man’s work in epistemology, Knowing and the Known, was co-written with Arthur (20 pts)",
        "Bentley. This man’s “instrumentalist” philosophy was similar to the American school of pragmatism, and he founded the Laboratory School of (10 pts)",
        "Chicago to promote experiential learning. This philosopher argued that education should be seen as a continuation of civil society. For ten points, name this liberal education advocate and author of Democracy and Education."
      ],
      "answer": "John Dewey"
    }
  ]
}